Boker Tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, Elul Tov אלול טוב, Elul Tov,
everybody reminded to do תשובה. teshuvah. Okay, pick up on today's דף
daf is, well, where we're up to is פו עמוד ב. P-Vav
amud bet. So we'll say that today's דף daf is פו, P-Vav,
we'll finish up פו P-Vav and do פז. P-Zayin. We pick up
with the משנה mishna on פו עמוד ב P-Vav amud bet and
we're still dealing with the הפרה hafarah of the husband. So let's
take a look. A lot of this has been focusing on what
constitutes עינוי נפש inuy nefesh or דברים שבינו לבינה devarim shebeino l'veina
and now we get a little bit more into the act of
הפרה hafarah itself. נדר אשתו וסבר שנדר בתו, Nedar ishto vesavar shenadar
bito, a man's wife took a vow, but he thought it was
his daughter, or right, two people that he can annul all their
vows. Or נדר בתו וסבר שנדר אשתו, Nedar bito vesavar shenadar ishto,
or his daughter and he thought it was his wife. נדרה בנזיר
וסבר שנדרה בקרבן, Nadra benazir vesavar shenadra bekorban, a woman made a
vow that she'd be a נזיר, nazir, but he thought that she
made some vow using the sort of קרבן korban terminology. Now it's
interesting, right, presumably it's not just a question of terminology. Let's say
it was נדרה בקונם וסבר שנדרה בקרבן Nadra bekonam vesavar shenadra bekorban
or something like that, you know, or she made a or she
or well, could be that's not even the best different example. But
let's say she just made a נדר סתם nedar stam and he
thought he used the word קרבן, korban, right? I mean, that would
be like a difference that would be without a distinction as it
were or that would not be so material. But presumably here it's
a very different type of a נדר nedar that he thought she
made, which actually could be like for the whole in a way
this is even more of a technical point than any of the
rest, because that could be his basis for annulling it might have
been on a faulty basis. Of course, maybe you could suggest the
same about wife and daughter, what he wants to annul for his
wife is not what he wants to annul for his daughter. So
there could be here some substantive reasons why he would not have
wanted to annul one way or the other. But it sounds like
the משנה mishna is not concerned with that. That basically the point
is you have to know whom you're annulling for and what it
is you're
annulling. נדרה בקרבן וסבר שנדרה בנזיר, Nadra bekorban vesavar shenadra benazir, or
she made a נדר nedar with the קרבן korban language and he
thought she made a נזיר נדר. nazir nedar. נדרה
מתאנים וסבר שנדרה מן הענבים, Nadra mite'einim vesavar shenadra min ha'anavim, she
made a vow not to eat figs and he thought she made
a vow not to eat grapes. Or נדרה מן הענבים וסבר שנדרה
מן התאנים, Nadra min ha'anavim vesavar shenadra min hate'einim, or the reverse.
In all these cases, he either did not know who made the
vow, what object it was made on, or what exactly the type
of the vow was. הרי זה יחזור ויפר. Harei zeh yachzor veyafer.
So in all those cases, he could he must be, let's read
it that he tried to be מפר meifer thinking those things, in
all those cases he must go back and be מפר meifer if
he wants it to be הופר. hufar. Another way to read this
that the רן Ran says, or both might be true is, he
was מקיים mekayem it thinking any of these things. That קיום kiyum
is not a problem because it's a קיום kiyum also based on
error and he is still enabled to go back and to be
מפר. meifer. So whether קיום kiyum or whether הפרה, hafarah, the גמרא
gemara is going to say this, not clear in the משנה, mishna,
you have to know for whom, what object, and what type of
a נדר. nedar.
Now he has until the end of the day
from when he realized he was mistaken? No, you still have ביום
שמעו. beyom shamo. You just made, well, actually what happens if in
there are certain errors we're going to get to in an upcoming
משנה. mishna. But that's when you sort of didn't realize that it
was a type of a נדר nedar you could annul or you
didn't realize that you had the ability to annul. Here he knew
all those things, he knew he was empowered to annul, and he
did, right. It's just that he got some of the details wrong
that would have allowed him to annul. So it does not seem
from this משנה mishna that that would be a basis for saying
that the that the idea of יום שמעו yom shamo stays away
from saying twenty-four hours, the basis of saying what constitutes the same
day would would make a difference. No, no, no, the day is
the day he heard because he did know that he had the
ability to annul, that it was a type of a נדר nedar
he could annul, and so on. Okay, so he presumably the time
period does not change, it goes from the time that he heard.
Now, speaking about hearing there's another interesting question here which I did
not have a full opportunity to explore, which is how did he
think it was his wife when it was his daughter or vice
versa? So you could think like, I don't know, he heard it
from behind the door, they have similar voices, you know, and he
just thought the other person was talking. But if you look at
the רן, Ran, the רן Ran says נדר אשתו וסבר שנדר בתו,
Nedar ishto vesavar shenadar bito, the second wide line or the end
of the second wide line, שאמרו לו שבתו נדרה ומתוך כך הפר
או קיים, She'amru lo shebito nadra umitoch kach hefer o kiyem, he
was it was reported to him incorrectly. So I'm thinking, reported to
him? I thought he had to hear it himself, right? I mean,
there was a whole discussion before whether a person can make a
שליח shaliach to annul the vows of his wife and the reason
that we said that a person could not was it required him
to be the one to hear it. He had to hear personally.
Okay? So I don't understand the רן Ran and I didn't see
others who said the same thing and I'm sure there are those
that ask on the רן, Ran, but I just did want to
point out that the רן Ran was interesting seeming to be that
you could know you know you do not need to directly hear
about it. Okay. So the simpler sense is that I would say
that he just heard from behind the door and he thought it
was was one was his wife and it was his daughter or
vice versa, yes.
Did you say if he confirmed but by mistake he could annul
it?
Yes. So the other way of reading this משנה, mishna, the גמרא
gemara will... and it will entertain both is that a קיום kiyum,
*kiyum* based on one of these errors is also not a קיום
kiyum *kiyum*. You have to know what type of vow, what type
of object and for whom you're doing it.
Is it both directions?
Exactly. So let's take a look at the גמרא gemara *Gemara*. למימרא
*L'memra* says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, דאותה דוקא *d'otah davka*. It says
if he will sort of prevent her, so the אותה *otah* is
דוקא *davka*. He has to know exactly who the woman is whose
vow he is annulling, his wife or his daughter, the אותה *otah*
is דוקא *davka*. Now not only is there an אותה *otah*, but
there's also how do you know that he has to know which
נדר neder *neder* he is annulling? So if you take a look
at תוספות *Tosafos*, at the רא"ש *Rosh* here at the bottom...
he says למימרא דאותה דוקא דכתיב והניא אותה דמשמע שמכיר האשה הנודרת
*L'memra d'otah davka dichtiv v'ini otah d'mashma she-makkir ha-ishah ha-noderes* because the
אותה *otah* here is the woman. ומשמע נמי הדכתיב והפר את נדרה
*umashma nami hadichtiv v'heifer et nidrah*, he will annul her vow, right?
So her vow, the specific one, שיכיר הנדר *she-yakkir ha-neder*, he has
to know which vow it is, okay, or what's the nature of
the vow is. Okay, interesting תוספות *Tosafos* by the way seems to
understand that the word אותה *otah* by והניא אותה *v'ini otah* refers
to the vow. If you look at תוספות *Tosafos* למימרא דאותה דוקא
*L'memra d'otah davka* on the right hand side, ולכך בעל Ba'al, צריך
שידע נדר neder שנדרה *ul'kach ba'al tzarich she-yeda neder she-nadrah*. He understands
the word אותה *otah* refers not to the woman but to the
vow. We've looked at the פסוקים *pesukim* before and we've pointed out
that the simple sense is that the אותה *otah*, והניא אותה *v'ini
otah* means prevent her, the woman, and נדרה *nidrah* is the vow.
So תוספות *Tosafos*, the רא"ש *Rosh* here has both. Okay, so because
it says her vow and her, it means specifically he have to
know the woman and the vow that he is annulling. Okay, so
now the top of פ"ז עמוד א' *Peh-Zayin amud aleph*, והא גבי
קרעים *ve-ha gabei kera'im* when it comes to doing a rending of
garments for אבלות *aveilus*, דכתיב על al על *dichtiv al al*, it
says well we'll see, because there the פסוקים *pesukim* seem to be
very specific in terms of identifying for what purpose or for whom
it is being done. דכתיב על שאול ועל יהונתן בנו *dichtiv al
Shaul v'al Yehonatan beno*, that דוד *David* rent his garments for שאול
*Shaul* and for יהונתן *Yehonatan* his son, so על על *al al*,
meaning very specifically identifying for whom the rending of the garments was
being done. Okay, so you would think that if you did it
for the wrong person it wouldn't count. ותניא ve'tanya *ve-tanya*, but we
teach in a ברייתא braita *beraisa*, אמרו לו מת meis, אביו וקרע
vekarah *amru lo met aviv ve-kara*, they said to a person that
your father died and he rent his garments, ואחר כך נמצא בנו
ve'achar kach nimtza beno, *ve-achar kach nimtza beno*, and then it was
discovered that actually it was his son who had died, רחמנא ליצלן
*rachmana litzlan*, יצא ידי קריעה kriah *yatza yedei keriah*, it counts, even
though it was done for the wrong person. So there it has
על *al* for X, which is certainly at least as specific as
והניא אותה *v'ini otah*, it specifically says it has to be for
X, and we don't require that it be for X. Now that
would have been a question not just on our משנה Mishnah *Mishna*,
that would be a question on its own terms, like what's the
logic about that that a קריעה kriah *keriah* for a wrong person
should work besides the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. I mean that in itself
just begs explanation. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
about that. אמרי לא קשיא *amri lo kashya*, it's not difficult, הא
בסתם והא במפורש *ha bistam ve-ha bemeforesh*. It depends whether you're explicitly
doing it for that person and you're wrong or whether in your
mind you're thinking the wrong person. Okay, what labels something to be
for X is not enough of what's going on in your mind.
It has to be because it's been made explicit. Explicit could be
like that you know that somebody says like oh your daughter did
it, I mean I guess going back to my question about that
he has to have heard it himself, he says oh rat, my
daughter made this vow, I'm going to annul my daughter's vow, that
would be that would explicitly label it as an annulling or as
a קיום kiyum *kiyum* or whatever for his daughter. Okay, whereas if
it was in his mind he thought something and he didn't say,
then maybe it will work. And similarly by the rending of the
garments, if it's like if somebody says to a person your father
died and he does קריעה *keriah*, that's labeled as a קריעה *keriah*
for his father. If he just thought his father died it would
not be. Now again that's not the simple sense of this ברייתא
braita *beraisa*. The ברייתא braita. *beraisa* says אמרו לו מת אביו *amru
lo met aviv*, so apparently it has been labeled. Okay, but let's
take a look though as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay,
so I mean the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says, look at the ר"ן
Ran *Ran*, the ר"ן Ran *Ran* says we'll have to re-explain this
ברייתא braita *beraisa*, the second narrow line in the ר"ן Ran *Ran*
here. הא דתניא אמרו לו מת אביו וקרע v'kara יצא לאו דוקא
דאמרו לו בפירוש מת אביו *ha detanya amru lo met aviv ve-kara
yatza lav davka d'amru lo be-perush met aviv*. They didn't explicitly say
it, because then that would have labeled it as a rending for
the father, אלא בשאמרו לו מת *ella be-she-amru lo met*. They said
to him so and so they said oh you know somebody died,
I'm so sorry, I heard that I heard that somebody died, וסבר
אביו ונמצא בנו *ve-savar aviv ve-nimtza beno*. And he assumed it was
his father and it's discovered it's his son, ובהאי יצא ידי קריעה
*uv'hai yatza yedei keriah*. That would be okay. So we're saying it
doesn't matter what's in your mind, it has to be it can't
be explicitly labeled for one person, that way it cannot it will
not be able to count for the other person. Okay, so let's
get back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* and see as the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* develops this. והתניא *ve-ha tanya*, and we taught similarly in
a ברייתא braita, *beraisa*, אמרו לו מת אביו וקרע *amru lo met
aviv ve-kara*. They said to a person that his they said to
a person that his father died and he and he rent his
garment, ואחר כך נמצא בנו *ve-achar kach nimtza beno*, and it was
discovered that it was his son, לא יצא ידי קריעה *lo yatza
yedei keriah*. He did not fulfill, because that was explicitly a rending
of garments for the father. אמרו לו מת לו מת, they just
said to him, "Oh, you know, it's somebody in your family died,
we're sorry to hear that," וכסבר אביו vekasavar aviv and he assumed
it was his father, וקרע and he rent his garments, ואחר כך
נמצא בנו, which it turns out was his son, יצא ידי קריאה,
yatza yedei kriya, then that's okay, his mind does not define the
reality that he had a relative who passed away and he did
קריאה kriya for the, you know, it wasn't like he accidentally was
trying, was like I don't know, was in, you know, accidentally ripped
his garment, apparently it is required at least he has intent to
do a קריאה kriya for the purpose of אבילות. aveilus. So that
nevertheless in the context that somebody died that satisfies. There's no need
to specifically intend the right person; it just can't be labeled for
the wrong person. Okay, so that's what we're saying by קריאה, kriya,
and presumably and therefore the על means it can't be labeled for
the wrong person. So presumably we would say the same by הפרה
hafara and קיום, kiyum that it doesn't have to have your mind
specifically for that right person as long as it's הפרה hafara in
the context of somebody whose vow you could annul and you did
the act of הפרה, hafara, presumably that satisfies as long as it's
not labeled for the wrong person. Now that seems a little bit
strange, right?
How the analogy works?
Yeah, because if anything we could say קריאה, kriya, I mean they're
all both hard, you would think either one you'd have to have
in mind the right person. But if anything קריאה kriya you could
say the reality that there's been some objective demonstration of something shattered
and broken in a particular real world context gives like meaning to
what that קריאה kriya meant regardless of what's in the person's head.
Whereas an act of annulling has to do with the fact that
you do not approve of something, or an act of קיום kiyum
that you do approve of something presumably requires, you know, that you
like know the circumstances, right? Otherwise it's like, you know, it's like
why should that be a meaningful act, especially if you think about
the fact that קיום kiyum, doesn't even require a physical activity. קיום
kiyum is just as we've seen before בלב, belev, right? הפרה hafara
requires it to be verbal if you remember this discussion before, קיום
kiyum does not. So certainly we should care about are you thinking
about the right person or not the right person. Okay, so it
is interesting that based on the analogy just because yes we do
see that by קריאה kriya sometimes it could work if it's not
explicitly labeled incorrectly that now we're suggesting that the same could be
by הפרה hafara and קיום, kiyum which I think would be strange.
Yes, there's a sense of lacking of not satisfying in terms of
tearing the clothing, you know, just like you didn't really resolve it.
Yeah. You didn't, I mean, you didn't really resolve that you were
tearing the clothing for the person that you really had loss for.
Right. I mean it doesn't solve that sort of the, you know,
internal psychological function. I mean again, it's not clear to me why
we very much do focus on the power of, you know, these
sort of practices of mourning and how they're so sort of psychologically
beneficial. You know, it's not like the rabbis were psychologists and they
were saying that that's that, you know, that it has to serve
that therapeutic function. You know, they were more interested I think in
it as an external demonstration, you know, of a, you know, a
ritual of mourning but which is not to deny the power that
it has internally. But, you know, but I don't think that they
saw that as like a necessary part. I mean it's an interesting
question. The Rav Soloveitchik talks about this at great length, what he
calls קיום שבלב, kiyum shebelev, that the external expressions of mourning ultimately
are fulfilled through, only when they're a manifestation of an internal experience.
So, you know, along those lines it's a very good question. Yes.
How do you resolve the contradiction in the ברייתות? braitot? One said
exact opposite: you are יוצא yotzei and you aren't יוצא. yotzei. Well,
it's through reinterpreting the first ברייתא braita, essentially.
Yes, that's where I went before. The first ברייתא is now being
reinterpreted.
And everyone agrees to that?
Yeah. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. So now that's the answer, that there's a difference between if
it's explicitly mislabeled and apparently הפרה hafara and הקמה hakama can also
work for the wrong person if it's not explicitly mislabeled. So let's
take a look. But we're not done. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi
amar, כאן בתוך כדי דיבור כאן לאחר כדי דיבור. kan betoch kedei
dibbur kan le'achar kedei dibbur. So רב אשי Rav Ashi is saying
presumably even if it's explicitly mislabeled we're going to be even more
lenient: it can work if it's corrected תוך כדי דיבור. toch kedei
dibbur. Okay, now normally תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur has to
do with something like a state of mind or normally we think
about it as like an opportunity to correct what you just said,
like edit, like ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם בורא פרי הגפן,
Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam borei pri hagafen, שהכל נהיה בדברו.
shehakol nihyah bidvaro. Okay, so, so it's like, you know, you're sort
of you can sort of still define your act or still have
an opportunity to make corrections over what you said and so on.
But it's less hard to it's less
easy to understand when we're not dealing with an act of speech,
right? When we're dealing with like this physical act of קריאה. kriya.
Let's take a look. And you don't even go back and correct
it and do something else that overrides; it's just your frame of
mind changes. So let's take a look. But he said presumably even
if it's explicitly mislabeled if you are corrected תוך כדי דיבור toch
kedei dibbur that would also work. Okay, כדי דיבור. k'dei dibbur. הא
דקאמר ha dekamar יצא ידי קריאה, yatza yedei kria, when does it
work? And now this goes back to the simple read of the
first ברייתא. The simple read of the first ברייתא sounds like even
if it was labeled as a tearing for the father, it works
when he discovers that it was his son. So there what we
said that it works if that שנמצא בנו בתוך כדי דיבור, shenimtza
b'no b'toch k'dei dibbur, it turns out that it was the son
בתוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, so then even if it was
explicitly labeled as the father, presumably it would be good if the
discovery was made within בתוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, that allows
it to be redefined. Okay, הא דאמרת לא יצא ידי קריאה, ha
d'amarta lo yatza yedei kria, that which we said you do not
fulfill your obligation, that's לאחר כדי דיבור, l'achar k'dei dibbur, after כדי
דיבור k'dei dibbur then it cannot be redefined. Okay, ותניא and we
taught similarly in a ברייתא, תניא tanya sometimes means a question, in
נדרים Nedarim it a lot means as a statement, and we taught
similarly in a ברייתא, מי שיש לו חולה בתוך ביתו, mi sheyesh
lo choleh b'toch beito, somebody has an ill person in his house,
meaning on his deathbed, ונתאלף v'nitalef and he fainted, וכדומה
שמת v'chedumeh shemet and it seemed that he had died, right, cuz
he looked like he had stopped breathing or whatever, וקרע and he
rent his garments ואחר מת v'achar met and then he actually had
died, בתוך toch so right afterward. Okay, got the timing a little
off. לא יצא ידי קריאה, lo yatza yedei kria, he did not
fulfill the obligation. And אמר רב שמעון בן פזי אמר רבי יהושע
בן לוי משום בר קפרא, amar Rav Shimon ben Pazi amar Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Bar Kappara, לא שנו אלא שמת אחר כדי
דיבור, lo shanu ela shemet achar k'dei dibbur, but then we have
the following gloss on this, that that's only if it's after כדי
דיבור, k'dei dibbur, אבל בתוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי, aval b'toch k'dei
dibbur k'dibbur dami, but if it's within it, it's like the speech
itself and therefore can be redefined. So now we are saying that
a קריאה kria it just cannot be mislabeled, it doesn't have to
have the right intention, it just cannot be mislabeled, and even a
mislabeling can be corrected right בתוך כדי דיבור. toch k'dei dibbur. Similarly
presumably by הפרה, hafarah, although we didn't say this explicitly, if a
person had the wrong person or whatever thing in mind, that's okay
as long as it was only what was in his mind, it
wasn't objectively labeled as such. And even if it's objectively labeled incorrectly,
if the discovery is made בתוך כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibbur, then
he gets to redefine it. Okay, now this is like as I
said very interesting because you could still say I don't get it,
right, how could the guy do קריאה kria for somebody who isn't
even dead yet? And I'd like the Monty Python routine, right, I'm
not dead yet. Okay,
anyway. So you're not fooling anybody. Anyway, okay. How could somebody do
קריאה kria for somebody who isn't even dead yet, and it counts
as an act of קריאה? kria? And it seems like, right, it's
one so like it's one thing to say if it's about my
frame of mind, I was thinking about one thing and then when
I sort of realized differently, somehow there's some continuity to my action,
so it's like that later intent can still define what I was
in the middle of the process that somehow I was in the
middle of. By the way, though, you know, it's easier when it's
like an act of speech, when you say בורא פרי העץ borei
pri ha'etz שהכל נהיה בדברו, shehakol nihiyeh bidvaro, because then you could
sort of say that you're saying new words that continues the act
that you're doing and gets to somehow redefine it here, you're not
continuing the act. I mean if the guy was doing קריאה kria
and let's say I don't know he had done the minimum שיעור
shiur of קריאה kria and then he was continuing to do קריאה
kria and he found out in the second part, maybe there you
could say well you're still part of the process, it can somehow
redefine. But here the guy did קריאה, kria, put it down, and
then he has some thought and that somehow redefines. And that's even
more difficult when not only is it that the physical scenario is
there to allow the קריאה kria to count, it was just that
it was mislabeled. Then you could say okay it's mislabeled, בתוך כדי
דיבור toch k'dei dibbur I still somehow am in the immediate sort
of context of it, my thought and my realization can somehow relabel
it. Okay that's like one thing to say something along those lines.
But to say that the guy wasn't even dead and you went
ahead the guy you did a קריאה, kria, so I don't understand.
It's not like you're somehow redefining what you did before. You want
something to work for an event that occurred later. You know, you're
sort of like trying to pull that previous act into the future.
So this is really the most difficult statement about בתוך כדי דיבור,
toch k'dei dibbur, or the whole circumstances don't yet exist. I don't
know, let's say I shake let's say I sit in a סוכה
sukkah בתוך כדי דיבור toch k'dei dibbur before שקיעה, shkia, anyway.
How do you do stuff before the circumstances exist yet? Or I'm
מקדש m'kadesh a woman and she gets her גט get בתוך כדי
דיבור toch k'dei dibbur from her other husband, from her first husband,
does that work? Anyway so it is very strange but what it
does sound like is that חז"ל Chazal are maybe trying to define
a concept of like simultaneity, you know, that it's sort of like
a principle of אי אפשר לצמצם. i efshar letzamtzem. How precise can
הלכה halakhah demand something? We're about actually we're in the middle of
a Rabbinical fellowship on the תשובות teshuvos of Rav Moshe, and you
know there's an interesting question right about like
how precise does the square of the תפילין tefillin have to be?
You know, what's when is it still considered to be a square?
You know, how do you measure the degree of precision required? So
this might be saying, no that's not enough. So this might be
saying. So this might be saying that the way in which like
we have a watch that only ticks off in תוך כדי דיבור
Toch k'dei dibbur increments, okay, not in seconds, it only ticks off
in תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur increments. So anything that occurs
תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur is occurring within the same period
of time. So that seems to be what you would have to
say according to this idea that a person did תוך כדי דיבור
Toch k'dei dibbur before the other person died, which again is much
more—we wouldn't say it by something else. Like I said, if I
gave a woman
a ring of קידושין kiddushin and she was already married to a
guy and he got her גט get תוך כדי דיבור, Toch k'dei
dibbur, I don't think it would take effect, right? So it is
easier to say that it's a question about just how do we
label the act. Was it labeled for X or not for X?
And somehow it has to do with my frame of mind can
be part of how something is being labeled and so on, but
that is very difficult in this case where the guy hadn't died
yet. So again, what we're saying is תוך כדי: Toch k'dei: A,
it doesn't have to intentionally be for the right person, it just
can't be mislabeled, and B, even a mislabeling can be corrected through
a—not relabeling interestingly, but through an awareness that occurs תוך כדי דיבור.
Toch k'dei dibbur. And then presumably similarly by הפרה hafarah and הקמה,
hakamah, which is also a big חידוש, chiddush, because there you would
think much more the right internal state is needed. Certainly by הקמה
hakamah that doesn't even require דיבור. dibbur. Nevertheless, presumably by parallel we
are saying that even if the person is thinking about the wrong
woman or about the wrong vow, as long as it's not explicitly
labeled as
such—you know, he hears a vow and he says I am מיפר
meifer it, right? Then there was a vow, he said he was
מיפר, meifer, he has the power to be מיפר, meifer, right? So
even though he thought it was his wife and it was his
daughter and he thought it was this and was that, he did
the act of הפרה. hafarah. A vow was heard, he has that
power, and therefore it takes effect and presumably even if it was
mislabeled—oh rats, my daughter made a vow, I'm מיפר meifer it—if he
finds out תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur that allows it to
be that awareness allows it to be relabeled. Yes, Charlie.
Didn't we have a מחלוקת machlokes already about if I marry a
woman after she gets divorced or after
she—yeah, that was רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. I was using that as
yes, that was in my mind because we did דבר שלא בא
לעולם davar shelo ba l'olam yesterday. But that was to take effect
after the divorce. I'm saying let's say I want it to take
effect now and she only gets her divorce a second later. Yes?
And wouldn't that be the same thing with a חכם? chacham? Like
you know David and I come there for a נדר neder, to
the בית דין Beis Din and you know they say alright fine
you know I throw my hat on and say oh regretfully and
תוך כדי Toch k'dei of your נדר neder or whatever. Right? I
don't know, I mean
like—that's
a good question because התרת
נדרים Hataras nedarim
has more to do with uncovering regret and error as opposed to
the more power of the act of הפרה. hafarah. So that might
require much more of the specific person, I mean the more specific
concrete awareness rather than just, well, the act was done in the
right context even if you weren't exactly aware. That could be. Now
I do want also point out by the way that the גמרא
Gemara, doesn't explicitly talk about הקמה. hakamah. I said before mentioned before
that it's possible to read the משנה Mishnah. so that הקמה hakamah
requires, we're also talking about the need of הקמה hakamah to be
specific. The גמרא Gemara. doesn't explicitly say that and as the ראשונים
Rishonim point out, the פסוק pasuk that the גמרא Gemara learned it
out from יניא אותה yania osah is a פסוק pasuk about הפרה.
hafarah. So I guess one could in theory say that all of
this is just about הפרה hafarah and הקמה hakamah maybe I don't
know goes by different rules. But again, if anything since הקמה hakamah
is internal, it even more would require awareness of the specifics. Okay,
but we should point out that the גמרא Gemara does not explicitly
mention הקמה hakamah although the ראשונים Rishonim say that that would follow
the same rules would require specific awareness is also being referred to
in the משנה. Mishna So let's just now read the גמרא's Gemara.
conclusion about תוך כדי דיבור. Toch k'dei dibbur. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this:
והלכתא, V'hilchasa, the הלכה halacha is, תוך כדי דיבור כדיבור דמי, Toch
k'dei dibbur k'dibbur dami, תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur counts חוץ
ממגדף ועובד עבודת כוכבים ומקדש ומגרש. chutz mimigadef v'oved avodas kochavim u'mekadesh
u'mgaresh. So there goes my validity to marry a woman before she
gets her גט get from her husband. Okay, so the times that
it does not work is a case of blaspheming and somebody curses
God and then says, "Oh, I didn't mean it.
I didn't mean God, I meant my mother-in-law or something." Okay, so
anyway, I'm sorry I shouldn't—okay, apologize to my mother-in-law. Okay, anyway, or
somebody is עובד עבודה זרה oved avoda zara and then he says,
"Oh, I didn't mean the בעל, I meant God" okay, when I
was bowing down and worshipping or whatever I was doing. Okay, or
he marries a woman and תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur he
says, "Whoops, wait I didn't mean it, I take it back." Or
he gives a woman a גט get and he says he didn't
mean it. In none of those cases it works. Now why not?
Okay, so what's the source to say it doesn't work? By the
way, the first thing I should point out that is a point
that all the ראשונים Rishonim say is the logic we have been
saying about תוך כדי דיבור Toch k'dei dibbur is either the extreme
version of a definition of simultaneity or like a question about your
דעת da'as and an act that's in the process that still has,
you know, ability to sort be defined because you're still directing the
act and it does have to with your frame of mind and
you can somehow still in the power of defining its nature. And
that all of those would be דאורייתא d'Oraisa concepts and it certainly
seems from this last thing that we only exclude— a handful of
cases which are real תורה Torah cases that as a rule this
is all דאורייתא, d'oraisa, right? I mean for God's sake, presumably we're
also applying it to the משנה mishna. which is about הפרה hafarah
and הקמה hakamah which is דאורייתא. d'oraisa. So all the ראשונים Rishonim
ask that this is a contradiction to רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam theory,
because רבנו תם's Rabbeinu Tam theory is that תוך כדי דיבור toch
k'dei dibur was a rabbinic תקנה takkana to help grease the wheels
of commerce, that allowed people the ability
to back out of a deal within the first few seconds, and
that was seen as somehow something like necessary to make it more
tolerable to do
business. That if you handed over the money to the person, say,
"Wait wait wait wait! I didn't finish my thought, you know what
I mean?" So he gave you a few second buffer to reconsider.
Now you could say that makes business harder because you can back
out. Anyway, but רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam made it into a rabbinic
תקנה. takkana. Here sounds very very much that it's דאורייתא d'oraisa and
it's a point that all the ראשונים Rishonim point out. Now what's
the reason that these things about מגדף, megadef, עבודת עבודה זרה, avodat
avodah zarah, קידושין kiddushin and גירושין geirushin are different? No פסוק pasuk
is being quoted. I mean no פסוק pasuk was quoted for תוך
כדי דיבור, toch k'dei dibur, but no פסוק is being quoted here
or no other basis. So the ראשונים Rishonim basically say it's just
basically מסברא mi-sevara because these things are so weighty that you cannot
say that you had your you did not have a you didn't
fully think it through and that you're reconsidering. Clearly your act was
intended and what you're thinking now is a different thought but it
cannot redefine your frame of mind. You would not have undergone something
as weighty and serious unless your first frame of mind was very
sort of clear. Okay so take a look at the ר"ן Ran
for example. The ר"ן Ran, says,
he says it's one, two, three, four, five lines down in the
wide lines, he says like this: ולא ידענא מילתא מאי שנא הני
ואינהו לרבנן הכי. V'lo yadana milta mai shena hani v'inhu l'rabanan hachi.
I don't know why these are different. ונראה בעיני דבשאר מילי דלאו
חמירי כולי האי V'nireh b'einai d'bishar mili d'lav chamiri kulei hai normal
types of things we engage in in the world that are not
as weighty, כשאדם עושה אותם לא בגמר דעתו הוא עושה. K'she-adam oseh
otam lo b'gemar da'ato hu oseh.
Whenever you do something you never you'll do things even if in
your mind you haven't a hundred percent made up your mind about
it. אלא דעתו שיוכל לחזור בו תוך כדי דיבור, Ela da'ato she-yuchal
lachazor bo toch k'dei dibur, you always are sort of holding on
to a little tentativeness in terms of it and "Wait, wait, I'm
still thinking it through," so you want to sort of still hold
there's a little reservation in your דעת, daas, which doesn't explain the
קריעה issue rending garment on a מת, but okay. Things that are
דעת daas related certainly. הני כיון דחמירי כולי האי, Hani kivan d'chamiri
kulei hai, since these are so weighty, אין אדם עושה אותם אלא
בהסכמה גמורה. Ein adam oseh otam ela b'haskamah gemurah. A person would
never do them until he had completely unreserved intention. ומשום הכי חזרה
אפילו תוך כדי דיבור לא מהני. u-mishum hachi chazarah afilu toch k'dei
dibur lo mahani. And therefore any attempt to retract is no good
because your דעת daas at the time is considered to have been
unreserved and complete. Okay. And then he goes on and quotes the
sort of position of רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam which he rejects. So
one way is to say that your דעת daas in these times
is considered complete. The other possibility is to say the action itself
is so weighty that it's not sort of the action speaks louder
than words as it were. So when the action itself is so
weighty you don't have the power to say I'm going to redefine
it. Meaning even if we said that your frame of mind was
the same, a person that marries a woman has the same he's
not a hundred percent sure but he's still going through with it
as he does when he's buying a car. Who knows? You see
I'm getting all ready for מסכת קידושין Masechet Kiddushin where we commodify
the woman. Anyway, but people always have these reservations. But because it
is something that is so weighty, either affects the status of another
person or does with a person's sort of relationship with God or
whatever, then הלכה halacha defines that the act cannot be redefined. An
act of that weight is final and cannot be redefined. So one
way or the other that those are the limits to תוך כדי
דיבור. toch k'dei dibur. So a very fascinating סוגיא sugya in the
גמרא, Gemara not fully explored here, but very important about this issue
about קריעה after the before the fact that the guy had died,
the most extreme example, and this difference between as I said whether
intent itself matters or the question about how the act was labeled.
All right now we go on to the next משנה. mishna. Yes?
There was a case the Queens חברה קדישא Chevre Kadisha had where
there were two women in a nursing home with similar names. One
died and they contacted the wrong sister. Oy, oy. And they ended
up doing all the rituals and then the living relative
called the shiva house.
Oh my God, oh my God, look at that. There you go.
Thank you for that. Okay wow pretty tragic. Okay, next משנה. mishna
אמרה, Amrah, a woman said, קונם תאנים וענבים שאלו שאני טועמת. konam
te'einim v'anavim she-eilu she-ani to'emet. These figs and grapes are forbidden to
me that I should not taste them or regarding my tasting of
them. קיים לתאנים, כולו קיים. Kiyam let'einim kulo kiyam. So this is
my guess and he was asked before exactly a case almost exactly
like this. The husband basically said I am מקיים mekayyem the idea
about
the figs. הפר לתאנים, Heifer let'einim, if however I annulled the
figs, okay, אינו מופר עד שיפר אף לענבים. eino mufar ad she-yafer
af la-anavim. It's ineffective until I annul also the grapes. The פשט
pshat of this משנה mishna is that it either works on the
whole נדר, neder. either everything or nothing. A
הקמה, hakama, affirming it, is even on a part affirms the whole
thing. An annulling about by part is not an annulling. To annul
you have to annul the whole thing. Which in a certain sense
makes sense. The נדר neder already exists. My wife already made it,
it's a real thing. To wipe it away requires, you know, more
strength than to just reaffirm what's already there. So even a little
reaffirming establishes it, roots it, okay, whereas if I want to annul
it, I gotta reject the whole נדר. All right, that's the simple
sense. I should point out that the ר"ן Ran suggests a different
read which I don't think is פשט pshat at all, which is
that it says if I am מפר meifer for the figs, it's
not מופר mufar for the grapes until I'm מפר meifer for the
grapes, but for the figs it does work. That הפרה hafara can
work on part. So הקמה hakama on part is a קיום kiyum
on the whole, הפרה hafara on part, the simple sense of the
משנה mishna is a הפרה hafara on nothing, but the ר"ן Ran,
reads says it's אינו מופר eino mufar for the grapes until he
הפר. heifer. I know, it's not פשט. pshat. But the ר"ן Ran
suggests a read of the משנה mishna. that הפרה hafara on part
does work for that part. It's not פשט. pshat. The פשט pshat
is all or nothing. To affirm what's already there a little קיום
kiyum works for the whole thing. A little הפרה hafara does not
work. You need to do a whole הפרה. hafara.
Okay, an ounce of קיום kiyum is better
than a, a little קיום kiyum. goes a long
way. Exactly. אמר קונם תאנה שאני טועמת וענבה שאני טועמת. Amar konam
te'einah she-ani to'emet va-anavah she-ani to'emet. Let's say she uses the words
שאני טועמת she-ani to'emet to separate out the two parts of her
vow. I won't eat a קונם Konam on this grape that I
won't eat regarding my eating it, and on this olive regarding my
eating it, not olive, whatever, fig, okay. So she didn't say the
word, I said grape first. Fig and grape. So she didn't say
the word קונם. Konam. If she said the word קונם Konam for
each one separately they're separate vows. She didn't say the word קונם
Konam for each one separately, but she did say שאני טועמת she-ani
to'emet separately. She used the sort of verb separately, okay. הרי הוא
שני נדרים, Harei hu shenei nedarim, that's sufficed to make it two
vows, and with the relevance that you do a קיום kiyum. on
one, it's not a קיום kiyum on the other. You do a
הפרה hafara on one, it works, okay, because now it really matters.
Do you call something one vow or two vows?
You know, let's say in my case, in my hybrid case, you
know, he's trying to do both at the same time. I like
it for לתאנים let'einim but I don't like it for לענבים. la-anavim.
So then what he, there's no way you could do that according
to the simple read of this משנה. mishna, You'd either have to
get rid of the whole thing or מקיים mekayem point. According to
the ר"ן, Ran what you could do is
you could do a הפרה hafara first on the part you don't
like and probably have to let the clock run out on the
other half and then it'll be a קיום. kiyum I wonder if
you could first do a הפרה hafara and then a קיום. Once
one half is removed, could the קיום on the other half work
without affecting the first half?
But according to the
simple read of the משנה, mishna?
then I've done
nothing?
Exactly. There's no way
you've done, exactly. Well, if you tried to do a partial הפרה,
hafara, you've done nothing, correct.
Or a partial הקמה? hakama?
No, then you've done a הקמה hakama of the whole thing.
No, I mean, partial as in הפרה, hafara, like I only did
this part and then I really said I don't like the other
part.
Doesn't matter. As soon as you did a הקמה hakama that works
for the whole thing, correct.
Really? So if I said I'm מקיים mekayem it for the תאנה
te'einah but not for the ענב, anav, so it's too late?
You mean like if you did a הפרה תוך כדי דיבור hafara
toch kedei dibbur of the הקמה, hakama, would it say that the
הקמה, hakama, would it neutralize the הקמה? hakama? I don't know. It's
a good question. Okay, let's see the גמרא. מאן מתניתין? Man matnitin?
Who's our משנה? mishna רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. It's רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael. דתניא תניא ברייתא. De-tanya tanya braita. אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו. Isha
yekimenu ve-isha yeferenu. Her husband will establish and her husband will annul
it. אמרה קונם תאנים וענבים אלו שאני טועמת. Amra konam te'einim va-anavim
eilu she-ani to'emet. I these figs and dates that regarding my eating
of it. קיים לתאנים kiyyem l'te'einim, כולו קיים. kulo kiyyem. If he
was established it for the figs it works for the whole thing.
A partial קיום works for the whole thing. הפר לתאנים, Heifer let'einim,
if he annulled for the
figs, okay, אינו מופר עד שיפר אף לענבים. eino mufar ad she-yafer
af la-anavim. Then it's nothing until he does the grapes as well.
Of course the פשט pshat is it's absolutely nothing. A partial הפרה
hafara is nothing. דברי רבי ישמעאל. Divrei Rabbi Yishmael. Those are the
words of רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, so our משנה mishna. clearly is
רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, that's exactly our משנה. Mishnah, ורבי עקיבא אומר,
Ve-Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says. הרי
הוא אומר, Harei hu omer, the verse says, אישה יקימנו ואישה יפרנו.
Isha yekimenu ve-isha yeferenu. The husband will establish, the husband will annul,
so it links the two so they have to operate with the
same
efficatiousness. מה יקימנו ממנו. Ma yekimenu mimenu. And how do we know
that a partial הקמה hakama works, right? I just gave you a
סברא svara for saying it, but what's the verse that says it?
So it's a play on words, יקימנו. yekimenu. So the מ mem
in the word יקימנו yekimenu means יקים, yakim, right? is from the
word יקים. yakim. But we're using the מ mem in a דרשה
drasha to say יקים ממנו. yakim mimenu. So as long as you
do a הקמה hakama even on only part of it, a piece
of it. of it, that works as a הקמה hakamah for the
whole thing. That's where we get the idea that a part הקמה
hakamah works. Or once we've established that for a הקמה, hakamah, so
אף יסירנו ממנו, af yesirenu mimmenu, so even for the הפרה, hafarah,
a partial הפרה hafarah works. So Rabbi Akiva agrees that it's all
or nothing, but he just says we'll take our lead from the
הקמה. hakamah. Since a partial הקמה hakamah is a full הקמה, hakamah,
a partial הפרה hafarah is a full הקמה. hakamah. That's Rabbi Akiva.
Now there's another possibility. Rabbi Ishmael would say back, מי כתיב יפר
ממנו? mi ketiv yafer mimmenu? It doesn't say... it says יקימנו, yakimenu,
you have the word by יקימנו, yakimenu, the ממנו mimmenu idea. You
don't have that word by יסירנו. yesirenu. For Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva
would respond, מקיש הפרה להקמה. makkish hafarah lehakamah. No, but it links.
מה הקמה ממנו אף הפרה ממנו. ma hakamah mimmenu af hafarah mimmenu.
Okay, so fine, that just spells out what we already read, that
yes it's true the דרשה drasha is by הקמה hakamah but they're
linked. So according to this read, it's all or nothing. We agree
that הקמה hakamah partial is all, and then there's the debate: Rabbi
Ishmael says הפרה hafarah partial is nothing, and Rabbi Akiva says הפרה
hafarah works like הקמה, hakamah, partial הפרה hafarah is like a full
הקמה. hakamah. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva, now we're going to
introduce a third opinion, because if you think about it, even assuming
it's all or nothing, what would be the three possibilities? Actually logically
there would be four, but okay. Anyway, the four, what are the
four possibilities? Partial is everything for both, partial is nothing for both,
partial works for הקמה hakamah and doesn't work for הפרה, hafarah, or
the reverse. Now the fourth possibility is not at all possible because
we've... right? Because there's no basis for saying a partial הפרה hafarah
works completely. But logically, מה הקמה עובד במה
שאתה מקיים הפרה עובד במה שאתה מפר.
ma hakamah oved
bema
she'ata mekayem hafarah oved bema she'ata meifer. Right.
But assuming we're all buying into the idea all or nothing, if
it's all or nothing there are four possibilities, right? Everybody got their
four possibilities? Partial הקמה hakamah partial הפרה hafarah is a full הקמה
hakamah full הפרה, hafarah, partial הקמה hakamah partial הפרה hafarah is nothing,
or partial הקמה hakamah is a full one, partial הפרה hafarah is
nothing. Okay, so we now have done two of the...
so there are really three of the logical four, we've done two
and now we're going to introduce the third. אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan,
זו דברי רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא, zu divrei Rabbi Yishmael veRabbi Akiva,
that's the position of Rabbi Ishmael and Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Ishmael says
partial הקמה hakamah is
everything, partial הפרה hafarah is zero. Rabbi Akiva says they're both everything.
אבל חכמים אומרים,
Aval Chachamim omrim, but
the sages say, מה הקיש הקמה להפרה?
ma hekish hakamah lehafarah? It works in the opposite direction.
מה הפרה מה שהפר הפיר אף הקמה מה שקיים קיים. ma hafarah
ma sheheifer heifer af hakamah ma shekiyam kiyam. Now the same way
הפרה hafarah works partially, הקמה hakamah works partially. Now really what you
would have liked to have said, which is the same way הפרה
hafarah partial is zero, הקמה hakamah partial is zero. Right. This sounds
like, yes, given the four... have I lost everybody now? Because what
it sounds like to me is what they're saying is, I had
avocados and grapes and I מפר meifer for avocados and I קיים
kiyam for grapes, that works. That sounds like exactly... I understand. I'm
just saying that's... yes, but the way we laid it out, it
sounded like everybody agreed that it was all or nothing. So if
it's all or nothing, you have the possibility הקמה hakamah and הפרה,
hafarah, okay, if it's all or nothing, so what are the four
possibilities? So one possibility is all all. One possibility is nothing nothing.
One possibility is all and nothing. And I guess in theory the
other possibility is all and nothing, but there's no reason to say
that הפרה hafarah is better than הקמה hakamah in that regard. We're
all assuming... so if you assume all or nothing and you start
by assuming that הקמה hakamah is more powerful. So these are your
possibilities, right? So this is the possibility of Rabbi Ishmael, this is
the possibility of Rabbi Akiva, and this could have been a third
possibility, the same way a partial הפרה hafarah is nothing, a partial
הקמה hakamah is nothing. Okay, but the last line in the גמרא
seems to question the all or nothing approach, seems to introduce a
new idea, that actually partial is possible. So comes in the last
line of the גמרא and says, who said it's all or nothing?
Partial is possible too. So this is partial and this is partial,
okay? And that's how the... that's the third opinion that rejects the
all or nothing type of an approach. Okay. I understand. Right. Okay.
All right. So let's take a
look. One
minute.
So if you take a look the ר"ן however, to keep the
nice structure that we had, has a different גירסא. girsa. If you
take a look four lines before the lines get wide in the
ר"ן, he says the following: לפיכך נראה גרסת קצת ספרים עיקר דגרסי
הכי. Lefikach nireh girsat ktsat sefarim ikkar degarsi hachi.
Here's a different גירסא girsa of that last punchline of the גמרא.
דגרסי הכי... Degarsi hachi...
three lines before the lines get wide... קצת ספרים עיקר דגרסי הכי:
K'tzat sefarim ikar degarsi hachi: אבל חכמים אומרים מה הפרה מה שהפר
לא הפר Aval chachamim omrim mah hafarah mah shehefir lo hefir אף
הקמה מה שקיים לא קיים. af hakama mah shekiyam lo kiyam. וכן
גרסת רבינו משה בר נחמן ז"ל בהלכותיו. vechen giras Rabbeinu Moshe bar
Nachman zal behilchotav. Okay,
so according to the ר"ן's גרסא, girsa, the last opinion is exactly
zero zero. The same way הפרה, hafarah, partial הפרה hafarah does nothing,
הקמה, hakama, partial הקמה hakama does
nothing. Okay, so basically one way of reading this is everybody agrees
that it's an all or nothing deal, okay, and therefore, and everybody
agrees that at least conceptually, partial הקמה hakama should be stronger. So
there are three logic possibilities and those three logical possibilities are spread
out. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says partial הקמה hakama is everything, partial
הפרה hafarah is nothing. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says partial is everything
for both, and whoever the חכמים chachamim are saying that according to
this other גרסא girsa that partial is nothing for both. Okay, so
that's the three logical possibilities if you take an all or nothing
approach. The other read of the last line of the משנה, Mishnah
of the גמרא rejects the all or nothing approach and says you
can have a partial הקמה hakama and you can have a partial
הפרה. hafarah.
Right,
so that would be the חכמים. chachamim. Well, depends how what your
גרסא girsa is. The ר"ן פוסק posek like the חכמים chachamim but
he says it's nothing for both. Okay, I want to tell you
what the רמב"ם Rambam says, what do we say on י"ג נדרים
י'. yud gimmel nedarim yud. I'll tell you what the רמב"ם Rambam
says. He probably has our גרסא, girsa, I don't know why I'm
saying that, because that would make it fun. עשה תאנים וענבים בין
בשבועה בין שאסר עצמו בכל המין וקיים לתאנים והפר לענבים או שקיים
לענבים והפר לתאנים מה שקיים קיים מה שהופר מופר וכן כל כיוצא
בזה. Asah te'einim va'anavim bein bishvuah bein she'asar atzmo bechol hamin vekiyam
lite'einim vehefir la'anavim o shekiyam la'anavim vehefir lite'einim mah shekiyam kiyam mah
shehufar mufar vechen kol kayotzei baze. So he has our גרסא, girsa,
partial works for both. Okay, yeah, like the חכמים. chachamim. Okay, אמר
קונם תאנים Amar konam te'einim and now we have the idea that
it's separate things if she says the word שאני טועם שאני טועם,
she'ani to'em she'ani to'em, that breaks it up into two נדרים. nedarim.
So the גמרא says, אמר רבא מתניתין רבי שמעון היא דאמר עד
שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. Amar Rava masnitin Rabbi Shimon hi de'amar
ad sheyomar shevuah lechol echad ve'echad. You might remember this that if
I take an oath, I that you say that I owe you
money and I denied it with an oath, I have to bring
a
קרבן korban and you know, be מוסיף חומש mosif chomesh etc. So
what's to define how many oaths I make? You all five of
you come to me and I borrowed a hundred dollars from each
of you, okay, because I'm regularly hitting up my friends, and then
each of you come and say where's the money you owe me?
And I say שבועה shevuah I don't owe any of you anymore.
So that's one oath and I take one קרבן, korban, bring one
קרבן korban if I'm lying. Let's say it says שבועה shevuah I
don't owe you and שבועה shevuah I don't owe you and שבועה
shevuah I don't owe you, that's five קרבנות. korbanot. Let's say I
say שבועה shevuah I don't owe you or you or you or
you or you, one or five? So that's the debate. So the
חכמים chachamim say it's not a separate
קרבן korban עד שיאמר שבועה לכל אחד ואחד. ad sheyomar shevuah lechol
echad ve'echad. So now, that's our משנה Mishnah because for our משנה
Mishnah, if you say קונם konam that I won't eat תאנים te'einim
or ענבים, anavim, it's still considered one נדר unless you break it
up more. But, I should say, it's not exactly parallel. If you
wanted to make it parallel, you would have to say קונם לכל
אחד ואחד. konam lechol echad ve'echad. קונם konam I won't eat תאנים
te'einim and קונם konam I won't eat ענבים anavim and קונם konam
I won't eat this, right? Is the fact that you said קונם
ענבים שאני טועם ותאנים שאני טועם konam anavim she'ani to'em ute'einim she'ani
to'em is not as much of a break up as reusing that
sort of key technical word קונם konam like the key technical word
שבועה. shevuah. But nevertheless, רבא Rava is saying it's close enough to
the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that you would require, you
know, something more significant to break things up into separate,
into separate נדרים. nedarim. Like רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi? Well, within the
discussion of what constitutes, you know, what do you call it, דברים
שבינו לבינה, devarim shebeino leveinah, you know, or עינוי נפש, inoui nefesh,
I don't think we're saying that he's the only תנא tanna speaking
here. Okay, or if you want you could say he's following this
opinion. All right, let's start, let's read the next משנה, there we
are, we're two דף daf ahead. I don't know what we're going
to do with all our, with all our reserve. יודע אני שיש
נדרים. Yodeia ani sheyesh nedarim. Okay, this is the issue that we
discussed, right, about when does the clock start ticking? יודע אני שיש
נדרים, Yodeia ani sheyesh nedarim, you know, let's just stop here. We're
far enough ahead and it's going to get a little complicated here
moving forward. Okay, so we'll pick up here tomorrow.